<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The rock of ages known, and foundation of many generations discovered after this long and dark night of apostacy, which shall never cover us again, because of the anointing, and though darkness may cover the nation, and gross darkness the people a little season, yet the Lord shall be unto his people and everlasting light, and their God their glory : also a prayer that the Lords people may be preserved to the end : also a few words to the King, and his council from the everlasting counsellor and Prince of Peace : also the Lords testimony against all persecutors of the innocent lambs of Christ, in whose light the nations of them that are saved must walk, and against all forms of worship whatsoever, taught by the precepts and commandments of men, which themselves are not led and guided by the spirit of the Lord : also a few words in answer to the last book of common-prayer / this is written in the fear of the Lord, and in the counsel of the everlasting counsellor, whose name is the Lord of Hosts, in Humphry Wolrich.</title>
            <author>Wollrich, Humphry, 1633?-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66861</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3298</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15328</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12596863</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12596863</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64069</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66861)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64069)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 971:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The rock of ages known, and foundation of many generations discovered after this long and dark night of apostacy, which shall never cover us again, because of the anointing, and though darkness may cover the nation, and gross darkness the people a little season, yet the Lord shall be unto his people and everlasting light, and their God their glory : also a prayer that the Lords people may be preserved to the end : also a few words to the King, and his council from the everlasting counsellor and Prince of Peace : also the Lords testimony against all persecutors of the innocent lambs of Christ, in whose light the nations of them that are saved must walk, and against all forms of worship whatsoever, taught by the precepts and commandments of men, which themselves are not led and guided by the spirit of the Lord : also a few words in answer to the last book of common-prayer / this is written in the fear of the Lord, and in the counsel of the everlasting counsellor, whose name is the Lord of Hosts, in Humphry Wolrich.</title>
                  <author>Wollrich, Humphry, 1633?-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Wilson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64069:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64069:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Rock of Ages known, AND FOUNDATION Of many Generations diſcovered, After this long and dark Night of Apoſtacy, which ſhall never cover us again, becauſe of the Anointing; And though Darkneſs may cover the Nation, and groſs Darkneſs the People a little ſeaſon; yet the Lord ſhall be unto his People an Everlaſting Light, and their God their Glory.</p>
            <p>Alſo a Prayer that the Lords People may be preſerved to the end.</p>
            <p>Alſo a few Words to the <hi>KING,</hi> and his <hi>Council,</hi> from the Everlaſting Counſellor and Prince of Peace.</p>
            <p>Alſo the Lords Teſtimony againſt all Perſecutors of the Innocent Lambs of Chriſt, in whoſe Light the Nations of them that are ſaved muſt walk: And againſt all Forms of Worſhip whatſoever, taught by the Precepts and Commandments of men, which themſelves are not led and guided by the Spirit of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Alſo a few Words in Anſwer to the laſt Book of
<hi>Common-Prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. <hi>53.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Have the workers of iniquity no knowledge? who cat up my People as bread.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Verſ. 6.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>When the Lord bringeth back the captivity of his People,
<hi>Jacob</hi> ſhall rejoyce, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall be glad.</p>
            </q>
            <p>This is written in the Fear of the Lord, and in the Counſel of the Everlaſting Counſellor, whoſe Name is the <hi>Lord of Hoſts,</hi> In <hi>HUMPHRY WOLRICH.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Wilſon</hi> in
<hi>Martins Le Grand,</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:64069:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:64069:2"/>
            <head>The Rock of Ages Known, and Foundation of many Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations Diſcovered, after this long and dark night of Apoſtacy, which ſhall never cover us again, becauſe of the Anointing, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>IN Patience, Meekneſs and Quietneſs, do we ſuffer, in Joy and Peace, and in the everlaſting Love of the Lord Jeſus do we lie down and reſt in him, notwithſtanding all the rage of the wicked, and their many wayes of cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty towards us; yet in all this, do we in patience paſſeſſe our ſouls, and a hiding place we feel in him who is the Lord our Righteouſneſs, in him onely do we truſt and hope, and of our hope ſhall we never be aſhamed we know, for in us we feel it as an Anchor to our ſouls in this ſtormy day, that is riſing as a mighty Tempeſt, to ſever the Chaff from the Wheat, that the fineſt of the Wheat may be eaten, and the Honey out of the Rock; O Lord, what ſhall become of <hi>London?</hi> O <hi>London,</hi> with thy Magiſtrates and Rulers, why ſhould ye be called a perſecuting people, after all your Fighting and Engagements for Liberty of Conſcience to ſerve the Lord, as moved by his Pure Eternal Spirit, and after the Tradition and Precepts of men no longer? O <hi>London,</hi> Repent, go not on in this cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el way of perſecuting an innocent people; return to the Lord, leſt thou be hardned as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> was, to his own deſtruction; O why ſhould ye be called a Bloody City? Why ſhould ye be reckoned with the Perſecutors in <hi>Queen Maries</hi> dayes, in the Generations to come? why ſhould ye be ranked with <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and her Rulers, out of which a Prophet could not periſh?</p>
            <p>O <hi>London,</hi> I pitty Thee, I pitty Thee, great is the miſery that upon thee and thy Rulers is coming, thy day is dark and gloomy, that is dawned, and come up to cover thee as a Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. O <hi>London,</hi> Do not go on to thy own ruine, the people whom thou fighteſt againſt, are bleſſed of the Lord that made Heaven and Earth, the Lord is their Strength and their Shield; and when he hath humbled them, and brought them low in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64069:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>Spirit, and purified them, &amp; made them more pure in heart, &amp; more perfect through ſufferings, then will he ariſe for their Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, yea, he will ariſe, the Mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it; it is good that we truſt in the Lord, even in the Name of the Lord all the day long; he that ſtood by us and in us, and hath delivered us out of many Tryals, and divers Tribulations, good is it for us to truſt in him to the end of our Pilgrimage; for we are ſtrangers to them that perſecute us, and they that hate us without a cauſe, know not our dwelling plac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: O <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> with thy Rulers, why ſhould ye be as <hi>Cain,</hi> Vagrants in the Earth? Why ſhould ye be droven out from the Preſence of the Lord, into the Land of <hi>Nod:</hi> Why wilt thou lay a burthen on thy own Conſcience, and gather Vexation and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh on thy own ſoul? The way ye take will not deſtroy us, the greater our burthens are, the more will the Palm Tree grow, and the Root ſhall ſpread it ſell abundantly, and the Branches ſhall break forth as a Morning without Clouds, in due ſeaſon, in his own time, that is, our Root, and bears up our heads under all our ſufferings, that we undergoe for his own Names ſake, in Patience we bear, giving our Backs to the Smiter, and our Cheek to them that pull off the Hair, becauſe of the Teſtimony to the Truth which we bear, and the VVord of his Patience which we keep; Therefore, in this day of darkneſs doth the Light ſhine forth, and in this time of tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, are we kept &amp; preſerved, who have believed in the Light Chriſt Jeſus, and whoſe hearts are fixed, truſting in the Lord, they are not afraid of evil tidings, nor of ſudden deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on when it cometh. O, let the Houſe of <hi>Aaron</hi> truſt in the Lord, He is their Hope and their Shield; O let all that know Him, truſt in Him at all times, and fear the Lord and his Goodneſs for evermore; him that hath withdrawn the Face of his Covering, and cauſed the Light of his Countenance to ſhine forth in our Tabernacles; He is unto his, that which Eye cannot ſee, nor Tongue expreſſe; and for declaring it, but for the ſakes of others, it is no matter, if hand ſhould be ſtill alwayes, and Tongue dumb for evermore; ſo that the Peace and Love of the everlaſting God and Father of all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation be but poſſeſſed, felt and enjoyned in the Heart and in the Soul; It is pure Liberty to the Captive, and that my
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64069:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>Soul doth feel and witneſs; it is bread of life to the hungry, and water of life to the thirſty ſoul; it warmes and refreſhes in the coldeſt night that ever came; it doth ſtrengthen the weak hands, and confirm the feeble knees; it makes the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate to rejoyce and break forth into ſinging, and the womb that hath been barren a joyful mother of many children: what ſhall I ſay to all that fear the Lord? be where ye will, he is company, and in the middeſt of wars, famine, and want, he is peac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> life, and fulneſs of every good thing; And though I am but of yeſterday in companion, yet I ſet to my ſeal that the God of the deſpiſed <hi>Quakers</hi> is the living and the true God; and their Worſhip, which is in Spirit and Truth, is only acceptable to the Lord: And further, for the Lord in this day of darkneſs that over thee, O <hi>England,</hi> is coming, and thou layeſt it not to thy heart; I ſay in the Light of the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal God of Heaven and Earth, that plucks up Nations, and plants them again, I bear my Teſtimony, and it is the Lords Teſtimony againſt all Forms of Worſhip, Forms of Prayer and Confeſſions of Sins, that are out of the life and power of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, being only taught by the precepts of men, and not led thereunto by the pure eternal Spirit of the Lord; I do witneſs againſt it all as a vain Worſhip, and in the ſight of the pure holy God, abomination.</p>
            <p>O <hi>England,</hi> in vain doſt thou worſhip; thy fear towards me, ſaith the Lord, is taught by the precepts of men, and yet thou layeſt it not to thy heart. O <hi>England,</hi> what haſt thou been fighting, plotting, and ſwearing ſo many years for a Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? doſt thou not yet conſider? wilt thou yet be ſo blind, as not to ſee that the Kingdom of Chriſt will not be ſet up with carnal weapons? O turn ye, turn ye to the Spirit of the Lord, that by your fighting, ſwearing, and deſtroying one another, hath been grieved: O that will ſhow you what ye are doing againſt the Lambs of Chriſt, which ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all; Love your Enemies; Pray for them that perſecute and deſpitefully uſe you, that ye may be like your heavenly Father.</hi> O King, and Parliament, &amp; Council, let all your Wiſe men of underſtanding conſult this matter, Was this the Lords way with you when he brought you in to the Government? was it not in peace? did <pb n="6" facs="tcp:64069:4"/>not his love and ſtrange acts towards thee, O King, almoſt perſwade thee there ſhould be no perſecution in thy Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions? Why art thou drawn aſide againſt the Lords Heritage, that can neirher plot, fight nor ſwear, either for or againſt any one? O conſider thine own Promiſe: <hi>Newgate</hi> in <hi>London</hi> hath above two hundred Priſoners that have lived hitherto peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably, men with their wives and little children in ſtinking holes, by vertue of a late Proclamation ſet forth in thy Name, to the waſting and ruine of many Families, which will lie as a burden upon thee, if thou lay it not to heart: All this is done againſt the Lords People, even againſt a People whom he hath bleſſed in this Generation, and choſen for his peculiar Treaſure in whom he delights to walk and dwell, and all that riſe up againſt them wil he rebuke for their ſakes, as he rebuked Kings in the dayes of old, ſaying, <hi>Touch not mine Anointed, and do my Prophets no harm;</hi> for them hath he choſen for a Peculiar People, and a Royal Prieſthood, and People in whom he will be glorified. O the eternal love of our heavenly Father! O the ancient Hils, the Hill of the Lord which is everlaſting, is known again to be what all the holy men and Prophets de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared it to be! <hi>O that men would praiſe the Lord for his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and for his wonderful works to the children of men! Who is a God like unto our God, or a Rock ſave the Lord? Happy are the People that have the God of</hi> Jacob <hi>for their ſhield, who hides them in the hollow of his hand that fear him, and carries them in his everlaſting arms of love,</hi> ſo that their ſtrength is renewed daily, and in their many tribulations they faint not; for in our hearts hath the pure eternal God ſhined forth, and the Creator of the ends of the Earth hath made known himſelf unto us; ſo doth his love ſhed it ſelf in our hearts, conſtraining us willingly to ſuffer the loſſe of any thing that in this world hath been dear unto us, ſo that Chriſt, his love, life and vertue may be but enjoyed (the loſſe of all is counted gain) ruling in our hearts, we in him, and he in us, our Lord and our God, putting down all Rule and Authority, and ſubjecting every high thought which in us hath ruled and lorded over the Heritage of God, binding his Fole to the Vine, and his young Colt to the choice Vine. This is our Victory over the World, which our Faith in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64069:4"/>the Power gives us continually; In this do we rejoyce and glory over the Perſecuter within and without: and as for our Cauſe, our righteous Cauſe, which is the Lords, and our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, which is no other but that his Truth may proſper, the Lord and his glory exalted in our hearts, teaching us to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip as we ought, as he hath promiſed in the latter day he vvill do; And as for us, let him do with his own what he pleaſeth, he hath bought us with a price. To the falſe Worſhip of the Nation we cannot bow at all, though the Furnace ſhould be heated ſeven fold hotter than it is; and vve ſuffer as Plotters, and unjuſtly numbred with Murderers; yet vve know me are clear as new-born children, and many of our enemies know it alſo, and have nothing to lay to our charge, but in the matter of our God and his Worſhip, and ere long it will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear it is, becauſe we cannot bow to
<hi>Baal,</hi> nor kiſſe him, in drinking the Whores Cup of Fornication, which is now hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out again to this Nation by the Merchants of
<hi>Babylon,</hi> whoſe day of wailing and bitter lamentation is nigh, even at the door: and as for us, let the Lord ſuffer them, if his will be ſo, to make merchandiſe of out bodies, as they have begun already, yet our ſouls are the Lords, and by his righteous power which we have put on, he is able to keep us from falling, or entering into any of the many temptations and ſnares that are laid for the Innocent; And as we ſtand with our confidence in the Lord our Righteouſneſs, and of his Righteouſneſs only to make mention, our Faith in the power of an endleſs life, our hearts ſhall not reproach us ſo long as we have a beeing, and our Sufferings are for Righteouſneſs ſake, becauſe we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not turn Idolaters, in ſetting up Dayes, and obſerving Times that the Lord did never command, but worſhip him as led and moved by his eternal Spirit.</p>
            <p>And we know the Letter doth not move at all, much leſſe doth it move any to confeſs Sin; as in the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book</hi> is ſaid; that is the Swearers, Liars and Perſecuters prayer, which to the Lord is an abomination, we cannot own for his ſake, neither do we confeſs our ſins, as taught of men, for this is hypocriſie; but as the holy Spirit that gives us power to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake them, teacheth us.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:64069:5"/>
            <p>O Friends, ye are all out of the way, that think God will be ſerved or worſhipped acceptably any other way but as led and guided by his holy Spirit. O what are ye doing? will ye limit the Lord in his People? this hath been the overthrow of many Governments. O conſider, will ye limit the Holy One of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to a few dead words in a Book, or a dead Confeſſion, taught by dead man whilſt in his ſins? What, do ye think the great God dwelleth in a dead Temple made with hands, and dead ſtones? Is this the Church of the Firſt-born, which Church is in God, whoſe names are written in Heaven? O ye Biſhops and learned men, will ye indeed be lords of our Faith? How can this be? <hi>My glory,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>will I not give to another.</hi> What, will ye be Lords over Gods Heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage? O will ye cauſe the poor to wander without bread, and take away the clothing from the naked, and leave him deſolate that hath no deliverer in the earth? O what are ye doing? will ye put out our eyes, whom the Lord hath opened, and then cauſe us to grind in your Mill? Is this to be eyes to the blind, and feet to the lame? O conſider, what ye are doing, ye Leaders of the people; <hi>Why ſhould my people be deſtroyed for lack of knowledge,</hi> ſaith the Lord? What, ſhall the Lord al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes be limited, that ye will not ſuffer him to teach his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? O conſider, conſider the Eternal ſees you, and all your wayes are naked and bare before him, whoſe eternal eye runs through all the dark parts of the Earth, and neither the Evil nor the Good is hid from his all-ſeeing Eye. O why will ye plot evil againſt the Lords Heritage? ye little know what a work ye have undertaken; the People whom ye are fighting againſt are bleſſed of the Lord; the duſt of <hi>Jacob</hi> that cannot be numbred, are they of, and they are of the ten thouſands of
<hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the off-ſpring of <hi>Jacobs</hi> God, which himſelf hath determined to eſtabliſh, and bring them into a Land, a good and a large Land, where he will make them a praiſe to Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, and the Children unborn ſhall call them the Bleſſed of the Lord, becauſe of Righteouſneſs, which is the girdle of their loyns, and the ſavour of their oyntment which is poured forth, ſhall their names be had in everlaſting remembrance.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:64069:5"/>
            <p>O pure righteous living Father of Heaven and Earth, do with thy People and Children what thou wilt, they are thine own, only keep them faithfull in thine own life, power and dominion; preſerve them, God eternal, thy Word of Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to keep, and Teſtimony to bear againſt all the falſe wayes and Worſhip that is now ſetting up and eſtabliſhing by a Law; Lord God Almighty, ariſe in the Conſciences of thy Enemies, and in their inward parts do thou convince them that are making void thy Law, thy pure righteous Law; in their own Conſciences ſhow them they are perſecuting thy People, and waſting thy Heritage, whom thou haſt choſen for thy peculiar Treaſure.</p>
            <p>O Lord, what are we? do with thine own what thou plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt, we are thy People, and the ſheep of thy paſture; <hi>Thy Name is one, and thy People one; what wilt thou do for thy great Name?</hi> Do what is good in thine own eyes, only bleſſe thy People, and in thy Arms carry thy Lambs, that none may take their Crown from them, O Lord God Almighty.</p>
            <p>A Form of <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> that is, the Swearers Prayer, the Lyars and the Drunkards Prayer, which prayes in the drunken ſpirit; but the Spirit of the Lord is not known by any ſuch, to teach them how to pray as they ought: Therefore wo to the crown of Pride, to the Drunkards of
<hi>England,</hi> whoſe glorious fading beauty is on the head of the fat valleys. <hi>Wo unto them,</hi> ſaith the Lord God, <hi>that are covered, and not with my Spirit;</hi> that pray, and not with my Spirit: theſe are a ſtink in my no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils, and as a fire that burneth all the day long; that dig deep, to hide their counſel from the Lord, and whoſe work is in the dark, that none ſhould know it.</p>
            <p>Wo unto them that go down into <hi>Egypt</hi> again for help, and whoſe hope is not in the Lord, but in the broken Reed of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> houſe, which houſe muſt be laid waſte and deſolate, without inhabitants, and the memorial thereof from genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to generation, warred with: Now come to the Spirit, which is within the Vail; the Lord is that Spirit, and when ye turn to the Lord, the Vail ſhall be rent, and the Covering deſtroyed and taken away that is on the head of the fat valleys;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64069:6"/>then ſhall living Waters flow out of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in that day, and the Spirit poured from on high, that ſhall teach you how to pray as ye ought.</p>
            <p>Then ſhall ye look upon Him whow ye are now piercing and perſecuting; piercing by your prayers, which are ſin, whileſt in the perſecution of the innocent Lambs of Chriſt ye are found; I ſay, then ſhall ye be in bitterneſs, and mourn, as one that mourneth for his firſt-born, that muſt be deſtroyed; and then it is not your calling the Innocent, <hi>Plotters,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring againſt them as
<hi>Murderers,</hi> which will clear you from the juſt and righteous judgments of the righteous God, who hears the ſighing of the Priſoners in the Pit, and whoſe ears are open unto their cry: <hi>The Lord openeth the eyes of the blind, the Lord looſeth the bands of the priſoners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then ſhall ye Biſhops mourn, and ye Prieſts mourn, and all ye Magiſtrates, every one that have a hand in perſecuting, ſhall mourn apart, when ye look upon Him whom ye have pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, both in your ſelves and the Lord Children, which in his ſight are dear and precious, and by him compared to the moſt fine Gold. O how are the precious Sons of <hi>Sion</hi> counted and eſteemed by you builders of <hi>Babylon,</hi> who are in Confuſion, and covered with thick darkneſs? What, do ye teach the poor people to pray, and call God their Father? What, do ye teach them to ſing
<hi>Davids</hi> Pſalms, and the Songs of <hi>Sion,</hi> in the Waters of
<hi>Babylon,</hi> and Land of Darkneſs? Is not that vain Worſhip that is taught by the Commandments and Precepts of men? Can the dead praiſe the Lord? And have ye not read, that <hi>the Prayers of the Wicked is Abomination to the Lord?</hi> Did not <hi>Peter</hi> bid <hi>Simon Magus</hi> firſt Repent, and then Pray, <hi>that the thought of his heart might be forgiven him:</hi> which was, that the Gift of God could be brought and ſold for Money? And have ye not need to repent of this ſin as well as <hi>Simon,</hi> which are ſelling your Gifts for Money all over the Nation? What, will ye pray, and teach others ſo to do, whileſt in the gall of bitterneſs and bond of iniquity your ſelves? O con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what ye are doing! will ye whip, perſecute, and impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon any that pray and preach only as the Spirit of the Lord guides and gives them utterances? Are theſe the weapons <pb n="11" facs="tcp:64069:6"/>which the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> did fight and War withal, or are they Antichriſts weapons, and ſuch as the high Prieſts and thoſe learned Rabbies did uſe againſt Chriſt our Lord and Maſter, which ſaid if this be done in the green <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ee, what will be done in the dry?</p>
            <p>Conſider theſe things ye Biſhops and all that would be counted Miniſters of Chriſt, what a foundation are ye laying for perſecution? have ye ſo ſoon forgotten your own ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, that ye are cauſing them thus to ſuffer that had no hand at all in yours?</p>
            <p>Conſider the words in your own Book of Common-Prayer, do ye deſire that ye may ſhew forth the light of a good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample for the glory of the Lord, and converſion of your ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies? Is this the way Chriſt took and commanded his to take, to fill priſons, holes and dungeons with ſuch as were Hereticks indeed, and to be caſt out and rejected? did he bid them baniſh, impriſon, and whip them? Now thus do you ſerve, your friends which tell you the Truth, and ſuch which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not obſerve dayes for his ſake, that hath commanded, ſaying, ſix days ſhalt thou labour, and do all that thou haſt to do: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conſider your wayes and turn to the Lord, for he is jealous, and a God that will not be mocked with words.</p>
            <p>This Way ye take may make many Hypocrites, and ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing friends, and they may bind themſelves with Oaths and Proteſtations, and yet in their hearts wait an opportunity to break all again. But by all your Jayles, ſpoiling of' our goods and bodies in ſtinking Priſons, two hundred and fifty together, having ſcarce room to lie one by another; I ſay this, by all theſe things you may make, your ſelves manifeſt as ye do, to be perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors of the innocent Lambs of Chriſt, but never ſhall ye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert enemies, nor turn one to the Lord by theſe things; &amp; <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ſhall ſee that ſaying fulfilled, The blood of the Martyrs, the ſeed of the Church. And as for our Religion, it came not up af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this manner, namely by the change of a King, a Parliament, Protector; but through all theſe changes that have been, it hath ſtood the ſame, and we the ſame in it, and to none of their commands in the matters of our God and his worſhip could we ſubmit, but choſe rather to ſuffer patiently by <pb n="12" facs="tcp:64069:7"/>them all; and our perſecutors are fallen, and we yet ſtand, and our confidence is the ſame as it ever was, not in the Arm of fleſh or weapons of War, but in the name of the Lord of hoſts that made Heaven and Earth, doth our hope ſtand; the Sea is his alſo and his hands prepare the dry Land, but as for the wicked they ſhall deal yet more wickedly, and they that hate us without a cauſe will become our cruel Enemies, that the Faithful may be made manifeſt whoſe love is to the Lord, and ſuch as are Hypocrites fearfulneſs may take hold on them.</p>
            <p>And now to your own Book, return a little and conſider it. Firſt, ye teach the Prieſt what he ſhall ſay, which is utterly contrary to the Scriptures, and Command of Chriſt therein, which ſaith, Take no thought what ye ſhall ſpeak before hand, for it is not you but the Spirit of the Father that ſpeaketh in you, he doth the work; and alſo contrary to their Practice, who waited at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> for the Spirit, and as that gave them utterance they ſpake. And it is better, as <hi>Paul</hi> faith, to ſpeak five words with the Spirit and underſtanding then ten thouſand in an unknown tongue; And it doth not profit at all to read, or hear read, Prayers, Praiſes, or Confeſſions of ſin, taught by the Traditions and Commandments of men, whilſt the tongue of the Learned is not known to ſpeak a ſeaſonable word to the weary, and alſo to the wicked.</p>
            <p>And alſo the people, which ye teach to ſay after him, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider in what a ſad ſtate their Souls are in towards the Lord, whoſe Holy Name ye teach them to pollute with their unclean lips, whilſt they are filled with iniquity, and unconverted: Is he the Lord their God ruling in their hearts? And whether they that live in perſecution, pride, covetouſneſs, and all manner of vanity, which the Lord hates, whether theſe be his people and the ſheep of his paſture? as in your Common Prayer is taught to all manner of wicked perſons, altogether unlike
<hi>David</hi> or the ſheep of Gods Paſture, which for his Names ſake were killed all the day long, and counted as ſheep for the ſlaughter? Let them that fear the Lord judge in theſe things, whether the deſpiſed
<hi>Quakers</hi> be not the People whom ye are perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting without a cauſe, &amp; filling your Priſons, holes and dungeons <pb n="13" facs="tcp:64069:7"/>withall; O let the Lord look down on our unjuſt ſufferings, in whoſe ſight we are clear as Children newly born into this world, from all manner of plotting or inventing either in thought, word or deed againſt the King, this preſent government or any other, ſince we were a People, called and choſen of the Lord to bear our teſtimony againſt the perſecution, oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and cruelty in them all; thus are we rewarded evil for good, to the ſpoiling of our Souls, and accounted your Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies alſo becauſe of theſe things.</p>
            <p>And now, what and if the juſt and Righteous God ſhould turn your own words upon your own heads again, and ſay, be it to you as in your morning Prayer you have ſaid, for his Elect ſake which cryes day and night, and for <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> ſake which gives him no reſt until he make her a praiſe in the midſt of the Earth. <hi>O Jeruſalem, Jeruſalem,</hi> thou wilt be a burden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſtone to this generation of perſecutors; If I forget thee, then ſhall my right hand forget her cunning, and my tongue cleave to the roof of my mouth. I ſay, what if the Lord give you the anſwer of your own Prayers, which you ſay and teach others? Theſe are the words, firſt ſpoken by the Prophet in the integrity of his heart, and the ſame good words have ye ſtole, and ſpeak them again, whilſt in your heart lodgeth perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution.</p>
            <p>O Lord my God (mark and be moderate and conſider your own words) if I have done any ſuch thing, or if there be wickedneſs in my hands; If I have rewarded evil to him that dealt friendly with me, (yea, I have delivered him, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any cauſe is my Enemy) then let my Enemy perſecute my Soul and take me let him tread my life upon the ground, and lay my honour in the duſt. Now muſt ye either condemn <hi>Davids</hi> words, and the Common Prayer Book alſo, or elſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny perſecution and leave it; elſe your own words will be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled upon yon and in your ſelves. Behold he travelleth with miſchief, he hath conceived ſorrow and brought forth ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, he hath graven and digged a pit and is fallen himſelf into the deſtruction that he made for others; but the Lord; hath prepared for him the Inſtruments of death, he hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained his arrowes againſt the perſecutors; and as for us <pb n="14" facs="tcp:64069:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>which ſuffer and are perſecuted for Righteouſneſs ſake, our help cometh from the Lord our God: and though the Lord ſuffer you to plow long and deep ſurrows on our backs, for the tryal of our precious Faith, yet when he hath ſearched our very hearts, and tryed our reins, then ſhall we be made more pure, as Gold that is tryed in the fire is, add that ſaying ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, <hi>The Lord delivereth the Righteous, and preſerveth them that are true of heart;</hi> then ſhall the Righteous be delivered out of all temptations: <hi>For the Lord knoweth how to deliver the Righteous out of them all, and to reſerve the Wicked to a day of Judgment to be puniſhed:</hi> the righteous Lord knoweth how to do all this in his ſeaſon. O the pure, endleſs, infinite love of our Father that bears up our heads, that in all our ſufferings we faint not, but in our heart can forgive our Enemies, and pray for them that know not what they do.</p>
            <p>And Friends, in your Morning-prayer, you pray for the King, that the Lord would ſet his watchful Providence as a continual fence about him, to be his guide and Counſellor, and never leave him; which in the truth of my heart do I deſire: which the Lord moſt certainty will do, if at the Spirit of the Lord he take counſel only, and not at you who limit it in his Lambs and Children, into whom he hath poured out of his Spirit, according as it is written, <hi>I will pour out my Spirit in the latter dayes upon my Servants and Handmaids, and they ſhall propheſie;</hi> this will I do unto them, and not forſake them, ſaith the Lord. And now Chriſt being come, and his Spirit given, which leadeth into all truth, even the Word of the <hi>Oath;</hi> (Mark) the Word of the <hi>Oath,</hi> which was before and ſince the Law, He ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all:</hi> and though <hi>Abraham, Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> and the Prophets, which were not come to the end of it, did Swear; and them that did Swear in Judgment, Truth and Righteouſneſs, the Oath was to them an end of all ſtrife, as ſaith the Apoſtle: but Chriſt when he came, which was greater than <hi>Solomon,</hi> and was before <hi>Abraham,</hi> he ſaith,
<hi>Swear not at all:</hi> And though ye may read the Angel in the
<hi>Revelation</hi> did ſwear, that time ſhould be no longer; yet in a certain place is it written concerning the Son, (which ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all</hi>) <hi>When he bringeth his firſt-begotten into the world, let the Angels of <pb n="15" facs="tcp:64069:8"/>God worſhip him:</hi> So whether they be Angels, Thrones or Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, Principalities or Powers, things in Heaven or things in Earth, they muſt all be ſubject to the Word of the Oath, which was ſince the Law; <hi>by whom, and for whom all things in Heaven and Earth were made and created;</hi> who is God eternal, and King immortal, that in all things he might have the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence, who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all.</hi> But this I ſay, the Lord did never, counſel King <hi>Charles</hi> the ſecond, nor never will, to fill all the Priſons, Holes and Dungeons in his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions with an Innocent People, for theſe things; As not for Swearing, and obſerving Days and Times, as <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> did, who filled
<hi>Jeruſalem</hi> with innocent blood; or as <hi>Jezebel</hi> did, when
<hi>Ahab</hi> ſtoned and took poſſeſſion of the Vineyard of
<hi>Naboth;</hi> but it was the Enemy of the Lord and his People, and the Council, when the <hi>Quakers,</hi> which are innocent as children newly born, were numbred with Murderers: It was no better than the Counſel of
<hi>Ahithophel,</hi> which the Lord turn into fooliſhneſs: I ſay, theſe were the Lords Enemies, and to King <hi>Charles</hi> in the end will not prove Friends; the Nation ſhall ſee, and conſider it diligently.</p>
            <p>For the Nation knows, yea, our Enernies themſelves will confeſs, the Quakers will not fight or plot againſt any for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſake towards God; but after they have owned the Light Chriſt, which is the Way and the Truth, many have left the Army both private Soldiers and Commanders, in ſo much that the Commanders, ſome of them, have ſaid, That if they ſhould not fight, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ing of the <hi>Scots</hi> would ſoon come in; and ſo by them were we perſecuted, as friends to you, and not meet to live in a Commonwealth, becauſe with carnal weapons w could defend our ſelves no longer: but their wiſdom di the Lord confound, and both them and their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour lies in the duſt, which durſt not truſt in the Lord, but made fleſh their Arm; but we remain the ſame, our Weapons the ſame, not carnal; and the Lord whom we ſerve, the ſame, and as able to deliver them that fear him as ever he was; his hand is not ſhortned, nor grown weak, but he is the ſame, and his years fail not; and to his People is he the ſame, and changeth not; ant therefore the Son of <hi>Sion,</hi> and Daughters
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:64069:9"/>of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> are not conſumed, whoſe hope is in the Name of the Lord, and not in Sword or Spear.</p>
            <p>And though the Priſons in <hi>London,</hi> and all over the Nation, be filled, that we can ſcarce lie one by another, two hundred and fifty in <hi>Newgate,</hi> men, their wives and children, yet dare we not Swear, nor obſerve Dayes, Chriſt having com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the contrary, unto vvhom vve do commit our Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Cauſe, and the keeping both of our ſouls, bodies and families, vvhich ye are vvaſting and endeavouring to deſtroy without a cauſe, who is the Prince of Peace, and ends the old Covenant, and puts an end to Swearing, obſerving of Dayes? Times and Seaſons, and brings in to the Reſt that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains, and was with, and in God before either Dayes, Times or Seaſons were commanded to be obſerved; But man being gone into the Darkneſs, out of the eternal and everlaſting Day, out of the Life, Power and Vertue that made him, and was inwardly ravened from the Spirit, and altogether reſtleſs and unſtable as waters that fail, knowing not a reſt in him that made him alwayes to keep holy day, and with himſelf at all times to be ſatisfied with peace, reſt and all manner of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>utterable felicity; as it is written, <hi>Eye hath not ſeen, nor ear-beard, neither hath it entred into the heart of man</hi> (in that ſtate) <hi>to conceive of the glory that is prepared for them that love him.</hi> O the infinite, endleſs, eternal depths of love, paſt finding our, which <hi>Paul</hi> was come into, in Chriſt the beginning and the end of Dayes, New-moons, and Sabbaths, and all ſuch things which he calls <hi>Carnal Ordinances,</hi> and mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> nothing perfect, being impoſed untill the time of Reform<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>on, and no longer, till Chriſt the better hope comes, who ſaith,
<hi>Old things are done away; all thinge are become new.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Bleſſed is he that reads and underſtands: for the time is at hand, the Spirit and the Bride ſaith, <hi>Come:</hi> even ſo ſaith my Soul, <hi>Come, Lord Jeſus, come quickly,</hi> Take unto Thee thy Great Power, and Reign in the midſt of thy Enemies.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <trailer>Let this be ſent to all Magiſtrates and Biſhops, by Friends, as moved.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:64069:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
